{"tossups": [{"question": "One leader of this city allowed Franciscan missionaries to try to convert him. They failed. Saint Louis died of dysentery while on a crusade to this city This city was established near the site of Mahdia, and it was ruled for centuries by its (*)  Hafsid Dynasty. Operation Torch involved a \"Run\" to this city, and this city rose to prominence after it was conquered by the Almohads. Mohammed Bouazizi sparked street protests in this city by self-immolating, and this city was grouped with Tripoli and Algiers in the \"Barbary States\" fought by the US. For ten points, name this city, the capital of a country named for it.", "answer": "Tunis", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tunis</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tunis", "Tunis"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Dagohoy Rebels in this country blocked European invasion of their land for 85 years. A wooden statue of Christ still in use today was given to this country's Rajah Humabon, and a passenger ferry in this country collided with an oil tanker in the deadliest (*)  peacetime naval disaster in history. A recent ceasefire in this country pacified its MILF rebels, and the communist Hukbalahap fought this country shortly after its independence. This country disputes Scarborough Shoal with China, and its current president committed thousands of extrajudicial killings as mayor of Davao. For ten points, name this country currently led by Rodrigo Duterte.", "answer": "Philippines", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Philippines</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Philippines", "Philippines"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One play published during this dynasty's rule featured a Stage Director in its opening scene, and one man sponsored by this dynasty developed methods for summing squares and was the namesake of his modern-day country's first satellite. This dynasty (*)  unsuccessfully campaigned against the Pallavas. Faxian wrote an account of his pilgrimage through this dynasty's lands. This dynasty was overthrown by a tribe it called the \"Huna\", known elsewhere as the Hephtalites. It's not the Maurya, but this dynasty developed from the rulers of Maghada and was ruled by men including Chandra Gupta. For ten points, name this early medieval Hindu dynasty ruled from Allahabad.", "answer": "Gupta", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Gupta</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Gupta", "Gupta"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "It's not President of France, but one holder of this position died of a stroke suffered while committing adultery. Another holder of this position apocryphally held the \"Banquet of the Chestnuts\", and a third holder of this position was attacked posthumously in the (*)   synod horrenda. This position was subject to increased noble control during the pornocracy, and the last English holder of this position was Nicholas Breakspear. One holder of this position wrote  Mit Brennender Sorge, and another wrote the  Syllabus Errorum, which condemned basically every political ideology except conservatism. For ten points, name this position held by three consecutive non-Italians for the first time since the 15th century by Benedict XVI, John Paul II, and Francis I.", "answer": "Pope  (accept Bishop of Rome, Pontifex Maximus, or Vicar of Christ)", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Pope</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Pope", "Pope"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Bishop of Rome, Pontifex Maximus, or Vicar of Christ"}, {"question": "The \"elliptical temple\" is located at this site. This site was taken over by the Rozwi Empire late in its history, and a polity ruled from this site was rocked by a civil war between (*)  Changamire and Mutota. A soapstone bird excavated at this site is a symbol of its modern-day country, and this site was ruled by kings titled monomotapa. Building at this site stopped in the 18th century, just before it came to the attention of Western archaeologists who thought it was the land of Ophir. For ten points, name this site located near Harare, the namesake of a modern country.", "answer": "Great Zimbabwe", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Great Zimbabwe</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Great Zimbabwe", "Great Zimbabwe"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A group of aristocratic intellectuals called the  jadids pushed for modernization in this country, and one Islamist movement in this country was founded by a former math teacher. That movement was attacked in the (*)  Andijan Massacre. This country's language is a modernized form of Chagatay Turkish, and this country faces a separatist movement led by the Karakalpaks. This country is the home of the Tughril Beg Madrasa. It's not India, but one insect-infested jail cell in this country's city of Bukhara was known as its \"black hole\". The daughter of this country's first post-independence leader, Gulnara Karimova, has been missing for years. For ten points, name this Central Asian country with capital Tashkent.", "answer": "Uzbekistan", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Uzbekistan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Uzbekistan", "Uzbekistan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This dynasty's shift from an in-kind tax system to one based on cash was one factor in its decline, and this dynasty began after its first emperor's father unknowingly had sex with the then-emperor's concubine. This dynasty was forced to hire nomadic help to suppress (*)  a rebellion about which the \"Song of the War-Chariots\" was written. This dynasty was followed by the Five Dynasties and Ten Kingdoms, and another poet of this dynasty died while drunkenly attempting to grab the moon while on a boat. This dynasty's peak years are often known as its \"fullness\". It contained China's only female emperor, Wu Zetian. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that succeeded the Sui and preceded the Song.", "answer": " Tang", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tang</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tang", "Tang"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This region's urine was highly prized as a dental hygiene product. One rebellion in this region was led by Viriathus, and the Saguntines were among the native inhabitants of this region. Emperors born in this region (*) included Trajan and Hadrian, and this region was divided into provinces named for Baetica and Tarraco. This region was conquered for Carthage by Hasrudbal, and the city of Cartago Nova in this region translates to \"New New City\". The diocese named for this region by Diocletian also controlled the province of Mauretania Tingitana, and, unlike Britannia, this region resisted conquest by the Gallic Empire. For ten points, name this Roman region that consists of modern Spain and Portugal.", "answer": "Hispania  (accept \"Lusitania\" before power)", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hispania</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hispania", "Hispania"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept \"Lusitania\" before power"}, {"question": "A group of farmers in India did this after seeing water dropletsfloat in the air. The Treaty of Ste. Claire-sur-Epte mandated that one of its signatories do this, and Duke Mojmir of (*)  Moravia did this only to have his brother take an opposing course. At the urging of Frumentius, King Ezana of Axum did this, and a Sioux chief's son who did this took the name of Charles Eastman and co-founded the YMCA. Refusing to do this action in reverse caused the execution of King Ella of Northumbria by Vikings. For ten points, name this action that usually involves baptism in a local river.", "answer": "Converting to Christianity", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Converting to Christianity</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Converting to Christianity", "Converting to Christianity"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A rubber-substitute company co-founded by this man inventedgum after he withdrew his sponsorship and left his business partners with several tons of chicle. During one campaign, this man hid in a convent with his army and shot through the holes in its walls. This man (*)  launched a coup against his own vice president and held a state funeral for his amputated leg, which was severed during his service in the Pastry War. This man signaled his intent to commit the act he is most famous for by playing  El Deguello, and during his final term, he sold land in the Gadsden Purchase. For ten points, name this Mexican General and politician who massacred Texans at the Alamo and Goliad.", "answer": "Antonio Lopez de  Santa Anna", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Antonio Lopez de  Santa Anna</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Antonio Lopez de  Santa Anna", "Antonio Lopez de  Santa Anna"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Don Alvaro Patin\u0303o instigated one war centered on this city, whose major economic activity produced both  tacana and  negrillos. Miguel Arzans y Urzua wrote the  Tales of this city, and this city was the site of the Vicun\u0303a War. This city's site was discovered by Diego Gualpa, and development took off after the discovery of the mercury (*)  mountain at Huancavelica. The  cerro rico was located in this city, whose mines were supplied by the  mit'a labor system. Local Andean languages referred        to this city as \"the mountain that eats men\" due to its high mortality rates. For 10 points, name this silver mining city in modern Bolivia.", "answer": "Potosi", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Potosi</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Potosi", "Potosi"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Lebor Gabala is titled for semi-legendary examples of these, which included one by the Milesians. In 2007, the Danish government formally apologized for one of these events that had occurred centuries earlier and resulted in the founding of its target country's capital. Roger Casement was hanged for (*)  assisting a German attempt at one of these, while another was led by Richard De Clare, more often known as Strongbow. One of these events initiated by Oliver Cromwell ended in the deportation of several natives to Barbados and the massacre at Drogheda. For ten points, name this type of event in which a country with capital Dublin was attacked by external forces.", "answer": "  Invasion  (accept equivalents) of  Ireland  (prompt on Viking raids)", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Invasion of  Ireland  (prompt on Viking raids)</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Invasion of  Ireland  (prompt on Viking raids)", "Invasion of  Ireland  (prompt on Viking raids)"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents"}, {"question": "This man fought on both sides of the American Civil War after being captured at Shiloh, then he was discharged from the Union army, and joined the Union Navy. This man grew up at St. Asaph's Union Workhouse in Wales before moving to the United States. The namesake of (*)  this man's boat, the  Lady Alice, broke off her engagement to him and married another man while he was on assignment for the  New York Herald. This man performed several secret missions for the International African Association, and his native porters gave him a nickname meaning \"the breaker of rocks\". For ten points, name this explorer, born John Rowlands, who famously met David Livingstone at Ujiji.", "answer": "Henry Morton  Stanley", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Henry Morton  Stanley</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Henry Morton  Stanley", "Henry Morton  Stanley"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This country organized the Salsipuedes Campaign against a native people who killed the explorer Juan Diaz de Solis. This country's group of 33 founding fathers are named for an adjective that remains in this country's official name. This country (*)  was riven for years by civil war between its Red and White Parties, and a guerrilla group named for an Incan rebel leader operated in this country. Giuseppe Garibaldi earned the nickname \"Hero of Two Worlds\" for intervening in a Civil War here. For ten points, name this country formerly known as Banda Oriental, which won its independence from Brazil.", "answer": "Uruguay", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Uruguay</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Uruguay", "Uruguay"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This group once led the town of Goldfield, Nevada as a de facto government. A poet associated with this group was  Battle of Hymns of Toil author Covington Hall. A philosophy of this group was known as \"folded arms\" and because members of this group preferred to strike on the job. A member of this organization was executed by firing squad in Salt Lake City after being accused of murder on circumstantial evidence. (*)  That man was poet Joe Hill. One leader of this organization is one of three Americans buried in the Kremlin. The membership of this organization fell after the First Red Scare and this organization was formed in a 1905 Chicago convention. For 10 points name this socialist labor organization that fought against the AFL and was founded by \"Big Bill\" Haywood.", "answer": "Industrial  Workers of the  World (Accept \"Wobblies\")", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Industrial  Workers of the  World</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Industrial  Workers of the  World", "Industrial  Workers of the  World"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "Accept \"Wobblies\""}, {"question": "One dynasty of this civilization was known as the Sealanders. In one ritual, the language of this civilization would be whispered in one ear of a bull, and the language of their conquerors in the other. This civilization (*)  was ruled by kings including Alulim, who held the throne for 28,800 years, according to their namesake \"King List\". One monarch said to have been discovered in a basket drifting through reeds as a baby served as cupbearer to a king of this civilization. Austin Henry Layard discovered the \"Royal Standard\" of these people's most important city. Cities of secondary importance to these people included Lagash and Kish. For 10 points, name these people who established three dynasties in the city of Uruk, located in Southern Iraq.", "answer": "Sumerians", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sumerians</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sumerians", "Sumerians"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "While fighting in its namesake country, Che Guevara described the victorof this war as \"bouncing from saloon to whorehouse\" in exile. The Mai-Mai militias were founded to fight in this war, and the casus belli of one of this war's participants was to protect (*)  the Banyarwanda. Much of the revenue required to sustain this conflict came from Coltan mines, and this conflict was known as \"Africa's World War\" due to the involvement of countries as diverse as Namibia and Chad. The city of Goma was the focus of much of this war, which began after Uganda and Rwanda attacked its namesake country. For ten points, name this late-1990s conflict in a country now led by Joseph Kabila", "answer": "Second  Congo lese Civil  War  (do not accept \"Congo Crisis\")", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Second  Congo lese Civil  War</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Second  Congo lese Civil  War", "Second  Congo lese Civil  War"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "do not accept \"Congo Crisis\""}, {"question": "An act named for this commodity was used by LeicesterHemingway to establish an unrecognized country he called \"New Atlantis\". This commodity's presence on Navassa Island led to a border dispute between the US and Haiti, and slavery (*)  continued to be practiced in mines for this quantity by confederate exiles in the Caribbean after the 13th amendment was passed. This commodity's recent exhaustion in Nauru has led to a budget shortfall that is largely met with Australian aid. This commodity's richness in Phosphates led to its use as a \"miracle fertilizer\" in the 19th century. For ten points, name this commodity excreted by birds and bats.", "answer": "Guano  (prompt on \"manure\")", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Guano</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Guano", "Guano"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \"manure\""}, {"question": "The Supreme Court ruled that part of this bill was an unconstitutional bill of attainder after it required some workers to file affidavits that they were not members of the communist party. A year of strikes including a massive one by railroad workers precipitated this act's passage. Employers were permitted to file a representation petition regardless of election conditions after the passage of this act. The main groups affected by this act were unable to collect money through a check off system (*)  and donate to political campaigns. This act overcame a presidential veto. This piece of legislation was a revision to the Wagner act and outlawed the closed shop, thus permitting \"right to work\" laws. For 10 points, identify this piece of legislation that limited the power of unions that was passed during the presidency of Harry Truman.", "answer": "Taft-Hartley  Act", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Taft-Hartley  Act</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Taft-Hartley  Act", "Taft-Hartley  Act"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One border dispute between these two countries was begun by Lyman Cutlar. Another, the result of differing interpretations of a certain hydrological feature, was over the Republic of Indian Stream. Another border dispute (*)  between these two countries was fought over a major potato-producing region, and the Northwest Angle is a surveying anomaly along the border between the two countries. The Rush-Bagot treaty fixed the border between these two countries. One popular political slogan wanted to fix the border between these two countries at \"fifty-four forty or fight\". These two countries fought the Arostook War and the Pig War. For ten points, name these two countries whose border includes sections in which Washington adjoins British Columbia.", "answer": "United States  and  Canada  (accept  United States  and  Britain )", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>United States  and  Canada</u></b>", "acceptable": ["United States  and  Canada", "United States  and  Canada"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept  United States  and  Britain"}], "bonuses": []}